Guide to the Marsden Hartley Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marsden Hartley collection
1885-1978
YCAL MSS 578
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.37
(36 boxes) + 4 objects, 1 cold storage
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, photographs, and other materials documenting the personal and professional affairs of Modernist-era painter Marsden Hartley. Writings contain notes and drafts, autograph and typescript, for numerous writings, chiefly essays. Correspondence is spread out over the many groupings in the collection and features large files of outgoing letters to Norma Berger, Hartley's niece, Carl Sprinchorn, and Adelaide S. Kuntz, as well as incoming letters from artists, writers, cultural figures, and institutions. Correspondents include Hart Crane, Robert McAlmon, Henry Miller, Marianne Moore, Arnold Ronnebeck, Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones, Gertrude Stein, Alfred Stieglitz, Carl Van Vechten, William Carlos Williams, and Edmund Wilson. There are also third-party letters between Berger and others concerning Hartley's work. Other materials include photographs, three oil paintings by Hartley, notebooks, and objects.
Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired chiefly through gifts from Norma Berger, 1950-1978, with additional material from other sources, 1952-2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
37 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some material available on microfilm.
Associated Materials
Printed materials cataloged separately at Za H255 +1.
Marsden Hartley (1877-1943)
Marsden Hartley, an American modernist painter known for his depictions of the Maine coastline and fishermen, was born on 4 January 1877 in Lewiston Maine. After his family moved from Maine to Cleveland in 1892, Hartley studied art at the Cleveland School of Art (1893-1898), then the New York School of Art, and the National Academy of Design. Hartley moved to Berlin in 1913 and spent much of the next two decades in Europe before returning to the U.S. in 1930 and to Maine in 1937. Hartley died on 2 September 1943 in Ellsworth, Maine.
Biographical information taken from "Hartley, Marsden (1877-1943)." Encyclopedia of World Biography. Detroit: Gale, 1998. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 15 May 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, photographs, and other materials documenting the personal and professional affairs of Modernist-era painter Marsden Hartley. Writings contain notes and drafts, autograph and typescript, for numerous writings, chiefly essays. Correspondence is spread out over the many groupings in the collection and features large files of outgoing letters to Norma Berger, Hartley's niece, Carl Sprinchorn, and Adelaide S. Kuntz, as well as incoming letters from artists, writers, cultural figures, and institutions. Correspondents include Hart Crane, Robert McAlmon, Henry Miller, Marianne Moore, Arnold Ronnebeck, Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones, Gertrude Stein, Alfred Stieglitz, Carl Van Vechten, William Carlos Williams, and Edmund Wilson. There are also third-party letters between Berger and others concerning Hartley's work. Other materials include photographs, three oil paintings by Hartley, notebooks, and objects.
Arrangement
Organized into fourteen groupings: 1950 Acquisition, Undated Acquisition, 1952-1953 Acquisitions, 1956-1976 Acquisitions, 1967 Acquisition, 1976 Acquisitions, 1978 Acquisition, Undated Acquisition, 1983 Acquisition, 1988 Acquisition, 1988 Acquisition, 1989 Acquisition, 2003 Acquisition, and 2005 Acquisition.
Modernism (Art); Painters -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Paintings (visual works); Photographic prints; Painters; Crane, Hart, 1899-1932; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; McAlmon, Robert, 1896-1956; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Ronnebeck, Arnold, 1885-1947; Sparhawk-Jones, Elizabeth, 1885-1968; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972
- 1950 Acquisition, 1900-1943; 3.96; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subgroupings: Writings, Letters to Norma Berger, and Other Materials.
  Scope and Contents
  Writings contain notes and drafts, autograph and typescript, for numerous writings, chiefly essays. The letters from Hartley to his niece, Norma Berger, span over four decades, dating from 1900 to 1943.
  Former call number: Za Hartley.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Norma Berger.
  - Writings
    - Index [of] manuscripts by Marsden Hartley, undated (Box 1)
    - "Bach for Breakfast", undated (Box 1)
    - "Canticle for October", undated (Box 1)
    - "Contrapuntal", undated (Box 1)
    - "The Eight Capucines", undated (Box 1)
    - "Essays on Rilke + J. P. Jacobsen", undated (Box 1)
    - "Hart Crane", undated (Box 1)
    - "Ironies Out of St. George", undated (Box 1)
    - "Letters Never Sent" / "Letters to the Dead", undated; 5 (Box 1)
    - "Mexico Essays by Marsden Hartley", 1932, undated (Box 1)
    - "Miscellaneous Papers Not Written by Marsden Hartley", 1940, undated (Box 1)
    - "Miscellaneous Manuscripts", 1940, undated (Box 1)
    - [Notes, Chiefly on Artists], undated (Box 1)
    - "Pamela the Bantam and Other Stories for Children", undated (Box 1)
    - "Patterns for Prayers", undated (Box 1)
    - "Provencal Preludes", undated (Box 1)
    - "Ryder", undated (Box 1)
    - Varied Patterns, undated (Box 2)
    - "Sixteen Typed Essays", undated (Box 2)
    - "Ten Essays in Hartley's Handwriting", undated (Box 2)
    - "Twenty Essays / M.H.'s Handwriting", undated (Box 2)
    - "Twenty Essays Related American Topics / M.H.'s Handwriting", 1930, undated (Box 2)
    - "Twenty Essays / M.H.'s Handwriting", undated (Box 2)
    - "Twenty-five Essays by M. Hartley", undated (Box 3)
    - "Twenty-five Essays European Topics / M. H.'s Handwriting", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Chariot of Fire", undated (Box 3)
    - "Be That As It May and Other Essays and Poems", 1941, undated (Box 3)
    - "Circus" [also "Elephants and Rhinestones"], undated (Box 3)
    - "Cleophus and His Own", undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Laughter of Steel and Journal Entries", undated (Box 4)
    - "Somehow a Past", undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - "The Spangle of Existence", undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - "Essays and Notations", undated (Box 5)
    - "Poems Miscellaneous Typed", undated (Box 5)
    - "Collections of Poems by Marsden Hartley Submitted to Dr. Henry W. Wells", undated; 21 (Box 6)
    - "Collections of Poems by Marsden Hartley Submitted to Dr. Henry W. Wells", undated; 11 (Box 7)
  - Letters to Norma Berger
    - Letters, 1900-1933; 48 (Box 8)
    - Letters, 1933-1943; 60 (Box 9)
  - Other Materials
    - Notebooks, undated; 4 (Box 10)
- Undated Acquisition, 1906-1945; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This group of material consists of letters to Hartley from others. Correspondents include artists, writers, cultural figures, and institutions, including Hart Crane, Robert McAlmon, Henry Miller, Marianne Moore, Arnold Ronnebeck, Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones, Gertrude Stein, Alfred Stieglitz, Carl Van Vechten, William Carlos Williams, Edmund Wilson, and others. There are also a number of correspondents with ties to Hartley's home state of Maine.
  Source unknown, but possibly Norma Berger.
  - A-C general, 1930-1943, undated (Box 11)
  - D-J general, 1928-1943, undated (Box 11)
  - K-M general, 1930-1943, undated (Box 11)
  - N-Z general, 1931-1943, undated (Box 11)
  - Aldington, R., 1941 November (Box 11)
  - Brigante, Nicholas, 1938-1940 (Box 11)
  - Bullitt, William, 1929, 1933 (Box 11)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1931-1943 (Box 11)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Crane, Hart, 1932, undated (Box 11)
    Includes photographs
  - Cronin, Vincent, 1942 (Box 11)
  - Dargan, Olive, 1941 (Box 11)
  - Dahlsberg, Edward, 1938-1941 (Box 11)
  - Davison, Frank, 1931-1941 (Box 11)
  - Downtown Gallery, 1931, 1933 (Box 11)
  - Evans, Abbie, 1940-1941, undated (Box 11)
  - Guggenheim, 1931-1942, undated (Box 11)
  - Hathaway, K. B., 1941-1943 (Box 11)
  - Jack, Peter Monro, 1937-1942, undated (Box 11)
  - Kuntz, Adelaide, 1932-1940 (Box 11)
  - McAlmon, Robert, 1940-1942 (Box 12)
  - Macbeth, William, 1940-1943 (Box 12)
  - Maine State Library, 1939-1941 (Box 12)
  - Mason, Francis, 1936-1937 (Box 12)
  - Metropolitan Museum, 1937-1942 (Box 12)
  - Miller, Henry, 1941, undated (Box 12)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1937-1941 (Box 12)
  - Nanatoni, Frank, 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Ronnebeck, Arnold, 1942 (Box 12)
  - Rosenberg, Paul, 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Sampter, Marian Vieth, 1932-1933 (Box 12)
  - Sisson, Richard, 1943 (Box 12)
  - Sparhawk-Jones, Elizabeth, 1936-1942 (Box 12)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1930 (Box 12)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1941 September 4 (Box 12)
  - Tebbetts, Leon, 1942-1943, undated (Box 12)
  - Templeton, Fay, 1932-1937, undated (Box 12)
  - Traubel, Horace, 1906-1910 (Box 12)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, undated (Box 12)
  - Villa, José Garcia, 1943 (Box 12)
  - Von Freyburg, Carl, 1909-1913, undated (Box 12)
  - Walker, Hudson, 1940-1942 (Box 12)
  - Wells, H. G., 1943 (Box 12)
  - Wheeler, Monroe, 1942, undated (Box 12)
  - Whitney Museum, 1932-1942 (Box 12)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1931-1940 (Box 12)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1939 December 13 (Box 12)
- 1952-1953 Acquisitions, [circa 1914]-1945; 0.21; (1 box) + 3 objects
  Organized into three subgroupings: Correspondence, Writings, and Artwork.
  This group of material consists of small acquisitions of letters from Hartley to others, one typescript carbon draft of "Digressions of a Cinemafano," and three oil paintings by Hartley.
  Acquired from various sources.
  - Correspondence
    - Anderson, Eleanor, undated (Box 13)
    - Brigante, Nicholas P., 1938-1940; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Davison, Frank C., 1940-1941 (Box 13)
    - Greason, Donald C., 1933-1945 (Box 13)
    - Guggenheimer, Richard, undated (Box 13)
    - Harris, Caryl, 1930 March 26 (Box 13)
    - Mommer, Paul, 1939 October 29 (Box 13)
    - Monroe, Harriet, undated (Box 13)
      Contains photostats
    - Sparhawk-Jones, Elizabeth, 1938-1942; 2 (Box 13)
    - Tweedy, Richard, undated (Box 13)
  - Writings
    - "Digressions of a Cinemafano", undated (Box 13)
  - Paintings by Marsden Hartley
    - An Abstract Arrangement of American Indian Symbols, [circa 1914-1915] (Box 21 art storage)
    - Collection of Numbers, Designs and Letters Seen by Me at the Beginning of the War in Berlin, [circa 1914] (Box 22 art storage)
    - Flaming Pool, Dogtown, 1931 (Box 23 art storage)
- 1956-1976 Acquisitions, 1906-1976; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  This grouping brings together several acquisitions consisting chiefly of correspondence. There are small groups of letters from Hartley to others as well as a large file of third-party correspondence between Hartley's niece, Norma Berger, and Carl Sprinchorn. Chiefly in English, with some material in German.
  Acquired from various sources, 1956-1976. Provenance traced on individual folders.
  - Berger, Norma, 1976 May 12 (Box 14)
  - Brigante, Nicholas, 1975 (Box 14)
  - MacKinnon, Frank, 1940 December 15 (Box 14)
  - MacKinnon, Normena, 1938-1943 (Box 14)
  - Marc, Franz, 1913, 1915 (Box 14)
  - O'Sheel, Shaemas, 1906-1945; 4 (Box 14)
    Includes third-party letters
  - Sprinchorn, Carl, 1918-1931, undated; 2 (Box 14)
  - Sprinchorn, Carl and Norma Berger, 1951-1965; 6 (Box 14)
  - Sprinchorn, Carl and Norma Berger, 1966-1971; 2 (Box 15)
  - Stettheimer, Ettie, 1934, undated (Box 15)
  - Stettheimer, Florine, 1931 (Box 15)
  - Tebbetts, Leon, 1942-1944, undated; 2 (Box 15)
    Includes third-party lettters from Arnold Ronnebeck
  - Photograph by Valente, [circa 1939-1942]
- 1967 Acquisition, 1916-1943; 0.42; (1 box)
  Gift of Carl Sprinchorn, 1967.
  Organized into two subgroupings: Letters to Carl Sprinchorn and Writings.
  The 1967 Acquisition contains approximately 90 letters from Hartley to Carl Sprinchorn dating from 1932 to 1943, as well as a drafts to five short writings by Hartley.
  Former call number: Za Sprinchorn.
  - Letters to Carl Sprinchorn
    - Letters, 1932-1943, undated; 11 (Box 25)
  - Writings
    - "The Jane", 1919 (Box 25)
    - "The Mystical Forest", undated (Box 25)
    - "The Two Mirrors", 1917 October 18 (Box 25)
    - Untitled, 1916, undated; 2 (Box 25)
- 1976 Acquisitions, 1899-1975; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subgroupings: Marsden Hartley Correspondence, Norma Berger Correspondence, Other Materials, and Writings.
  Contains letters by Hartley and others and drafts for several essays.
  Gifts of Norma Berger.
  - Marsden Hartley Correspondence
    - Berger, Mrs. J.S.W., 1899 December 1 (Box 16)
    - Berger, Norma, 1900-1943; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Hartman, Eva, 1945 July 30 (Box 16)
    - Traubel, Horace, undated (Box 16)
      Contains typescript copies
    - Waldeck, Nina, 1942 January 14 (Box 16)
  - Norma Berger Correspondence
    - Hartman, Eva, 1945 July 30 (Box 16)
    - Pfenninger, Anna, 1942 October 23 (Box 16)
    - Sprinchorn, Carl, 1954-1975; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Williams, Florence, 1951 April 30 (Box 16)
  - Other Materials
    - "Heortlea" [notes], undated (Box 16)
    - "Ironies Out of St. George", undated (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1932-1943, undated (Box 16)
    - Notes on death of K. Hathaway, undated (Box 16)
  - Writings
    - "A. P. Ryder", undated (Box 16a)
    - "Cleopatra and His Owne: A North Atlantic Tragedy", undated (Box 16a)
    - "Dear Elizabeth Sparhawk-Jones", undated (Box 16a)
    - "The Education of an American Artists: Second Stage - or the Intake of Modernism", undated (Box 16a)
    - "Her Eight Monkeys", undated; 2 folders (Box 16a)
    - "Elephants and Rhinestones: A Book of the Circus", undated (Box 16a)
    - "The Latest Derain", undated (Box 16a)
    - "On the Subject of the Mountain", undated (Box 16a)
    - "The Voice is Everything", undated (Box 16a)
    - "Wesley Adams: Maine Trooper", undated (Box 16a)
- 1978 Acquisition, 1923-1978; 1.05; (4 boxes) + 1 object
  Organized into two subgroupings: Correspondence and Other Materials.
  Correspondence consists of third-party letters between Norma Berger and others concerning the work of Hartley. Correspondents include scholars, museums, and publishers. Other Materials include photographs and objects.
  Dates attributed to folder contents listed below are circa dates.
  - Correspondence
    - Archives of American Art, 1965-1976 (Box 17)
    - Bates College, 1954-1978; 2 (Box 17)
    - Bernard, Dallas, 1970-1971, undated (Box 17)
    - Branden Press, 1974-1976 (Box 17)
    - Burlingame, Robert, 1976-1978 (Box 17)
    - Chidsey, G. Alan, 1976 (Box 17)
    - Dane, Howe, 1952, 1968 (Box 17)
    - Gillespie, Gary, 1973-1977 (Box 17)
    - Gropper Art Gallery, Inc., 1967 (Box 17)
    - Harrison, 1964-1972 (Box 17)
    - Hartley, Marsden, 1949-1964, undated; 2 (Box 17)
    - Homer, William, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Little, David B., 1964-1976 (Box 18)
    - Lynch, Michael, 1976-1977 (Box 18)
    - Maine, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Misc[ellaneous], 1950-1978; 2 (Box 18)
    - O'Gorman, 1973 (Box 18)
    - Russell, Leon B., 1965-1976 (Box 18)
    - Schaefer, Bertha, Gallery, 1968-1972 (Box 18)
    - Schwartz, Sanford, 1975-1976 (Box 18)
    - Scott, Gail R., 1975-1978 (Box 18)
    - Seabury Press, 1973-1975 (Box 18)
    - U.S.C., 1967-1969 (Box 18)
    - Viking Press, 1949-1973 (Box 18)
    - Yale University, 1949-1978 (Box 18)
  - Other Materials
    - "Pears and Apples," lithograph, 1923
    - Photographs, undated; 4 (Box 19)
    - Shoulder tabs from Carl von Freyburg's uniform, undated (Box 19)
    - Typewriter, undated (Box 24 art storage)
  - Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
    - Photograph of Hartley by Alfredo Vincente, [circa 1939-1942] (Box 20)
    - "Pears and Apples," lithograph, 1923 (Box 20)
- Undated Acquisitions, [circa 1885]-1957; 1.58; (6 boxes)
  Organized into two subgroupings: Photographs and Other Material.
  This group of material includes hundreds of photographs and other papers. The photographs include images of family members, Hartley, other people, places, and artwork by Hartley and others. Other papers consist chiefly of printed material, including clippings, ephemera, such as postcards, exhibition catalogs, and publicity, and magazines.
  - Photographs
    - Photographs and other material, circa 1885-1957, undated; 7 (Box 26)
    - Photographs and other material, 1924-1948, undated; 5 (Box 27)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 28)
    - Photographs and other material, 1940s; 5 (Box 29 (Oversize))
  - Other Material
    - Other Material, 1938-1943, undated; 6 (Box 30)
    - Scrapbook, 1936-1942, undated (Box 31 (Oversize))
- 1983 Acquisition, undated; 1 folder
  Gift of Bertram Sarason, 1983.
  Former call number: Uncat Za File 28.
  - Transcriptions of letters to Hartley from Gertrude Stein, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 32)
- 1988 Acquisition, 1925-1954; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  The 1988 Acquisition features a lengthy correspondence from Hartley to Adelaide S. Kuntz dating from the mid 1920s through mid 1950s. Other materials include a photograph of Hartley and a card file containing an index of Hartley's letters to Kuntz by date and first line.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 67.
  Organized into two subgroupings: Correspondence and Photographs and Other Papers.
  Gift of Mr. and Mrs. John Kuntz, 1988.
  - Correspondence
    - Kuntz, Adelaide S., 1925-1937; 12 (Box 32)
    - Kuntz, Adelaide S., 1938-1954, undated; 7 (Box 33)
    - O'Shay, Monica Barry, 1939-1940 (Box 33)
    - Others, 1931-1937, undated (Box 33)
  - Photographs and Other Papers
    - Photograph of Marsden Hartley, 1948 (Box 33)
    - Other Papers, 1928-1945; 3 (Box 33)
    - Card File, undated (Box 34)
- 1988 Acquisition, 1913-1932; 1.3; (3 boxes) + 1 cold storage
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 75.
  Gift of Karl T. Dworak, 1988.
  Organized into three subgroupings: Correspondence, Printed Material, and Photographs.
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1913-1929, undated; 3 (Box 35)
  - Printed Material
    - Printed material, 1929-1932, undated; 3 (Box 35)
  - Photographs
    - Photographic postcards, undated (Box 36)
    - Nitrate Negatives, undated (Box 37 (Cold Storage))
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Reference Prints, undated (Box 38)
- 1989 Acquisition, undated; 1
  Gift of Karl T. Dworak, 1989.
  - Two drawings, undated (Box 39)
- 2003 Acquisition, undated; 0.21; (1 box)
  The 2003 Acquisition consists of drafts, autograph manuscript, of short essays on artists and travel assembled by Hartley for a collection entitled "Varied Patterns".
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 570.
  Gift of Tony and Elspeth Vevers, 2003.
  - "Varied Patterns: A Book of Human Values", undated; 28 (Box 39)
- 2005 Acquisition, 1920-1945; 0.5; (1 box)
  - Microfilm, 1920-1945 (Box 40)